Finding Aid for Right to Life of Michigan Records 1972-1986
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Right to Life of Michigan Records 1972-1986
Right to Life of Michigan.
2 linear feet
Pro-life citizens group. Administrative materials, records of area committees within the organization, subject files, and affiliate organizations' materials consisting mainly of local right-to-life organizations; and correspondence and press statements.
88176 Bt 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The records of Right to Life of Michigan (donor no. 7514 ) were deposited with the library on January 27, 1988.
The record group is open for research.
Right to Life of Michigan, formed as Voice of the Unborn in 1972, is the leading anti-abortion organization in the state with approximately 115 local affiliate chapters and 110,000 members. It is a loosely organized group of local pro-life clubs that came together to oppose Proposal B, an abortion reform referendum in 1972 that would have legalized abortion in Michigan during the first twenty weeks of pregnancy. Proposal B was defeated by a large margin, but that issue became moot with the United States Supreme Court Roe v. Wade decision of January 22, 1973, which made constitutional the right of a woman to terminate her pregnancy and at the same time struck down state anti-abortion statutes.
Following Roe v. Wade the pro-life movement in Michigan gained strength. The National Right to Life Committee convention, held in Detroit in June, 1973, attracted over 1,200 delegates. In 1974, Voice of the Unborn incorporated as Michigan Citizens for Life. The organization consisted of nine geographic regions, with headquarters in Grand Rapids. New local chapters appeared in nearly every region of the state, but the strongest support continued in the west.
Through media campaigns, meetings, information packages sent to schools, colleges, and the general public, newsletters, and a lobbyist in Lansing, Michigan Citizens for Life informed the public and legislature about pro-life views of abortion. Michigan Citizens for Life also pressed for a human life amendment to the Constitution of the United States. A representative of the organization sits on the National Right to Life Committee in Washington, DC to help coordinate national and state activities and to further the goals of the pro-life groups. The name of the organization was changed to Right to Life of Michigan in the late 1970s. In 1985, it began participation in a nationwide pro-life boycott of the Upjohn Company of Kalamazoo to protest that company's role in the research, development and manufacture of drugs used to induce abortion.
The records of Right to Life of Michigan document the administration and activities of the leading anti-abortion organization in Michigan. The records have been divided into the following Series: Administrative, Committees, Topical Files, Affiliate Organizations, and Correspondence and Press Relations.
Subjects:
Abortion.; Michigan--Politics and government--1971-1980.; Michigan--Politics and government--1981-1990.; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-; Pro-life movement--Michigan.
- Administrative 1973-1982
  Administrative, 1973-1982, contains the organization's bylaws, board of directors meeting minutes, 1973-1981, convention reports, 1975-1981, financial materials, including monthly financial reports, 1973-1981, and projected budgets, 1975-1980, and planning sessions and proposed plans, 1981-1982.
  - Bylaws 1976-1977, 1980 (Box 1)
  - Board of Directors Minutes
    - 1973 (mostly agendas) (Box 1)
    - 1974 (Box 1)
    - 1975 (Box 1)
    - 1976 (Box 1)
    - 1977 (Box 1)
    - 1978 (Box 1)
    - 1979 (Box 1)
    - 1980 (Box 1)
    - 1981 (Box 1)
  - Conventions 1975-1981, 7 volumes (Box 1)
  - Financial
    - Audit Reports 1979-1980 (Box 1)
    - Budgets 1975-1980 (Box 1)
    - Major Gifts Reports 1977-1980 (Box 1)
    - Monthly Financial Reports
      - 1973-1974 (Box 1)
      - 1975 (Box 1)
      - 1976 (Box 1)
      - 1977 (Box 1)
      - 1978 (Box 1)
      - 1979 (Box 1)
      - 1970 (Box 1)
      - 1981 (Box 1)
    - Special Reports 1975-1978 (Box 1)
  - Planning Session 1981 (Box 1)
  - Proposed Plan 1981-1982 (Box 1)
- Committees 1974-1980
  Committees, 1974-1980 contains material on three of the organization's committees: the Educational Committee for Life, 1974-1979, the Michigan Pro-Life Educational Committee, 1976-1978 (succeeded by the Educational Committee for Life), and the Political Action Committee, undated and 1980.
  - Educational Committee for Life 1974-1979 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Pro-Life Educational Committee 1976-1978 (Box 1)
    Succeeded by Educational Committee for Life
  - Political Action Committee Undated, 1980 (Box 1)
- Topical Files 1972-1981
  Topical Files, 1972-1981, is arranged alphabetically and covers a variety of topics. Included is euthanasia, government agencies of Michigan, interaction with, 1973-1979, and Hollister Committee (Death and Dying Task Force), 1977-1981.
  - Euthanasia 1977-1979 (Box 1)
  - Government Agencies
    - Michigan Department of Public Health 1975-1979 (Box 1)
    - Michigan Department of Social Services
      - Dempsey Controversy 1977-1978 (Box 1)
      - General 1975-1979 (Box 1)
    - Michigan Women's Commission History 1973-1979 (Box 1)
  - Hollister Committee (Death and Dying Task Force) 1977-1981, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Legislative Day 1980 (Box 1)
  - Legislative Reports 1981 (Box 1)
  - Lobby Day 1981 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Abortion Reform Referendum-Campaign to defeat 1972 (Box 1)
  - Position Descriptions Undated, 1976, 1979 (Box 1)
  - Ryan, Justice James (Michigan Supreme Court) Candidacy 1974-1976 (Box 1)
  - Voter Identification 1981 (Box 1)
- Affiliate Organizations 1973-1983
  Affiliate Organizations, 1973-1983, is an alphabetically-arranged listing of local chapters of Michigan Right to Life. Material on some affiliates is minimal, while others are better documented, especially Bay City Right to Life, Berrien County Right to Life, Dickinson County Right to Life, Greater Lansing Right to Life, Holland Right to Life, Kalamazoo Right to Life, Lifespan, Inc. (Royal Oak), Lifespan Macomb County and East Wayne, Lifespan Wayne County West, Marquette County Right to Life, and Northern Michigan Right to Life. Much of the material for the above-mentioned affiliates, as well as for others, is in the form of newsletters. (Issues of the statewide newsletter are also available; they are cataloged and housed separately).
  - Member Organizations List 1975 (Box 1)
  - Albion Right to Life undated (Box 1)
  - Alpena Right to Life 1976-1979 (Box 1)
  - Barry County Right to Life 1976-1977 (Box 1)
  - Battle Creek Right to Life 1975-1979 (Box 1)
  - Bay City Right to Life 1970-1983 (Box 1)
  - Berrien County Right to Life 1976-1979 (Box 1)
  - Cass County Right to Life 1977 (Box 1)
  - Central Michigan Right to Life (Isabella County) 1974-1978 (Box 1)
  - Chippewa County Citizens for Life 1977 (Box 1)
  - Clio Right to Life 1979 (Box 1)
  - Cooley Law Students for Life undated (Box 1)
  - Copper Country Right to Life 1977-1978 (Box 1)
  - Dickinson County Right to Life 1978-1983 (Box 1)
  - Eaton County Right to Life 1979 (Box 1)
  - Flint Area Right to Life 1975-1982 (Box 1)
  - Grand Rapids Right to Life Undated, 1974, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Greater Lansing Right to Life 1978-1983 (Box 1)
  - Gwinn Area Right to Life 1978 (Box 1)
  - Hillsdale Right to Life 1977, 1979 (Box 1)
  - Holland Right to Life Undated, 1975-1982 (Box 2)
  - Huron Chapter for Michigan Citizens for Life 1973-1978 (Box 2)
  - Jackson Citizens for Life 1975, 1979 (Box 2)
  - Kalamazoo Right to Life 1975-1983 (Box 2)
  - L.I.F.E. Muskegon 1972-1973 (Box 2)
  - Lifespan, Inc. (Royal Oak) 1971-1983, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Lifespan Macomb County and East Wayne 1975-1979 (Box 2)
  - Lifespan Oakland County Undated, 1977 (Box 2)
  - Lifespan Washtenaw County Undated, 1975-1979 (Box 2)
  - Lifespan Wayne County West 1973-1979, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Marquette County Right to Life Undated, 1970-1983 (Box 2)
  - Mecosta Citizens for Life 1979 (Box 2)
  - Northern Michigan Right to Life 1973-1981 (Box 2)
  - Oceana Citizens for Life 1973-1978 (Box 2)
  - Owosso Right to Life 1975, 1977 (Box 2)
  - Port Huron 1978 (Box 2)
  - Protection of Life (Lansing) 1974-1977 (Box 2)
  - Pro-Life of Lenawee County 1978 (Box 2)
  - Region 8 Right to Life 1970 (Box 2)
  - Right to Life of North Kent 1977-1981 (Box 2)
  - Right to Life of Michigan (Box 2)
  - Saginaw County Right to Life 1977-1981 (Box 2)
  - St. John's Right to Life 1977 (Box 2)
  - St. Thomas Respect Life 1977-1978 (Box 2)
  - Tri-Cities Right to Life (Grand Haven) 1976-1978 (Box 2)
  - Tri-County Right to Life (Benton Harbor) 1976-1978 (Box 2)
  - Upper Michigan Right to Life (Marquette) 1975-1977 (Box 2)
  - Western Michigan Citizens for Life 1973-1978 (Box 2)
  - Wexford-Missaukee County Right to Life 1975-1979 (Box 2)
- Correspondence and Press Relations 1973-1986
  Correspondence and Press Relations, 1973-1986, contains correspondence, 1973-1981, and statements to the press, 1977-1986.
  - Correspondence
    - 1973-1977 (Box 2)
    - 1978 (Box 2)
    - 1979 (Box 2)
    - 1970-1981 (Box 2)
  - Press Relations
    - 1977-1981 (Box 2)
    - 1982-1983 (Box 2)
    - 1984 (Box 2)
    - 1985 (Box 2)
    - 1986 (Box 2)